Guide to the Lawrence (Larry) Barnes collection AD.MC.105
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Lawrence (Larry) Barnes collection
1946-1974
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Barnes, Lawrence, 1923-2003
AD.MC.105
2.63 Linear Feet in 3 boxes.
Photographic slides, documents, calendars, publications, and ephemera, documenting the activities of engineer Lawrence "Larry" Barnes, while working for the Arabian-American Oil Company (ARAMCO) in Saudi Arabia from the late 1940s through the 1970s.
Conditions governing access
The collection is open for use in the Reading Room of the Archives and Special Collections department of the NYU Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate source of acquisition
Acquired by purchase, 2022.
Arrangement
The Lawrence Barnes collection is arranged in five series: 1. Larry Barnes: personal, 2. Administrative: general, 3. Staff: general, 4. Community: general, 5. Printed material. There was no original order to the collection, so the current system of arrangement was devised by the processing archivist.
Content Description
The Lawrence (Larry) Barnes collection consists of photographic slides, documents, calendars, publications, and ephemera, documenting the activities of engineer Lawrence "Larry" Barnes, and other community members in and around Dhahran, Saudi Arabia, while he worked for the Arabian-American Oil Company (ARAMCO) from the late 1940s through the 1970s.
The collection represents a few discrete areas of Barnes' activities during this period. The first series, "Larry Barnes: personal," mostly consists of biographical documentation, such as drivers licenses and on-boarding documents related to the beginning of his career with Aramco in 1947. Included in this series are monthly job logs, which date mostly from 1949 to 1951 and list the various locations and types of projects he was engaged in as an electrical engineer during this period, ranging from work at oil production sites to the installation of electrical systems in palaces of local rulers in Hofuf and Riyadh.
The second series, "Administration: general," consists of a report that Barnes authored for a construction project in Uthmaniyah, but primarily consists of files related to document discovery in a legal case brought against Aramco by a grand jury of the U.S. District Court in Washington, DC, accusing the company of engaging in practices that led it to be considered as part of an international oil cartel. The next series "Staff: general," consist largely of memoranda sent to Aramco staff about various policies, but also includes a series of photographic slides of an oil facility in Abqaiq. In addition, two telephone directories, a classified directory of offices of Aramco and a directory of the Dhahran Airfield (operated by the U.S. Air Force) are also included here.
The series "Community: general," contains materials that focus on the social and community life of Aramco employees and their families, chiefly in Dhahran but also at the company's training facility in Sidon, Lebanon. The last group of items, in the series "Printed Material," consists chiefly of spiral-bound Girl Scout calendars collected by Barnes, which contain notations about his family's activities and events during the period covered (from the early 1960s to 1978), but even more so, which also contain images from photographers employed by Aramco's Public Relations department, depicting scenes from Aramco's community and also from throughout the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. A school yearbook from 1974 provides a glimpse of the elementary and junior high school run by Aramco, and at which Barnes's wife, Marion, apparently worked. The last item, a boxed set of educational materials produced by Aramco and titled "You discover, Saudi Arabia" (originally published by Coward-McCann, 1963, but reprinted in 1969) is included in its original box, containinig posters, coins, postage stamps, worry beads, and a booklet, all meant for classroom use.
While the contents of the Barnes Collection are somewhat fragmentary, the materials provide an outline of some of the early experiences of Larry Barnes upon joining Aramco as a new employee in 1947, the living conditions of expatriate employees during the 1950s, and some glimpses of their social lives in Dhahran during the 1960s and 1970s.
Petroleum industry and trade -- Saudi Arabia; Social conditions; Dhahran (Saudi Arabia); Electrical engineers -- Saudi Arabia; Arabian American Oil Company
- Lawrence Barnes: personal, 1947-1968
  - Air transport instructions, June 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Drivers license (temporary, with photograph), Cyprus, September 19, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Drivers licenses (2), Dhahran, Saudi Arabia, undated, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Job logs, February - December 1949 (Folio 3 (O.S.), Folder 1)
  - Job logs, January - December 1950 (Folio 3 (O.S.), Folder 2)
  - Job logs, January - August 1951, September 1952 (Folio 3 (O.S.), Folder 3)
  - Letter, from Saudi Arabian Airlines (John Geiser), expressing thanks for assistance during accident in Dhahran, August 13, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter, to family from Aramco, with instructions for mailing packages to Barnes, June 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Administration: general, 1952-1978
  - Legal: U.S. District Court of D.C., Grand Jury, subpoena for documents, August 1, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Legal: Memoranda and notes, regarding subpoena and document search, August 20 - September 6, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Legal: memoranda regarding subpoena and document search, September 7 - 9, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Management Guide," Arabian American Oil Company, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Report: "Construction of Uthmaniyah GOSP" [gas oil separator plant], 27 December 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Staff: general, 1946-1962
  - Arabic lessons [printed study material, undated, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memorandum: "Instruction Sheet on Preparing Christmas Packages" [for family members of Aramco employees], September 1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorandum: "Instructions for handling accompanied and unaccompanied baggage", January 1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Memorandum: "Personnel and Employment Information", August 21, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Memorandum: "Royal Commission Agreement Status" [excerpts, regarding living conditions of staff], January 1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Memorandum: "Supplemental Personnel Policies - Men" [signed by Lawrence Barnes], May 1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographic slides, color (36): scenes of various installations, primarily Abqaiq, without captions, 1962 and undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Sidon Training Center: General Information" (8 pages), January 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Telephone directory: Dhahran, classified section [listings by department and office], undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Telephone directory: Dhahran Airfield, Second Air Division [U.S. Air Force], September 1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Community: general, 1947-1956
  - Circular: "Fire Prevention Bulletin", undated, circa December 1947 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Recreation: "Attractions" [schedule of events], undated, circa June-July 1956 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Recreation: "Activities Calendar" (Aramco Employees' Association), October 1947 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Recreation: "A Tour of Al Hasa Oasis," compiled by F. Vidal (Conducted Tours, Recreation Section), November 1952 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Recreation: "Softball at Sidon," by "Boulos" Schwarzenau [summary of softball game among staff at Sidon Training Center], March 29, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Recreation: "ACS Defeats Training Center" [summary of softball game at Sidon Training Center], undated, circa 1952 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Publications, 1961-1978
  - The Dhahran Girl Scout Calendar - Date Book, 1961 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - The Dhahran Girl Scout Calendar, Date Book, 1962 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - The Dhahran Girl Scout Calendar, 1963 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - The Dhahran Girl Scout Calendar Date Book, 1964 (Box 2, Volume 4)
  - The Girl Scout Calendar, Dhahran, 1965 (Box 2, Volume 5)
  - The Girl Scout Calendar, Dhahran, 1966 (Box 2, Volume 6)
  - Girl Scout Calendar Date Book, 1967 (Box 2, Volume 7)
  - The Girl Scout Calendar, Dhahran, 1968 (Box 2, Volume 8)
  - The Girl Scout Calendar, Dhahran, 1970 (Box 2, Volume 9)
  - The Girl Scout Calendar, Dhahran, 1971 (Box 2, Volume 10)
  - The Girl Scout Calendar, Dhahran, 1972 (Box 2, Volume 11)
  - The Girl Scout Calendar, Dhahran, 1974 (Box 2, Volume 12)
  - The 1977 Girl Scout Engagement Calendar: 30th Anniversary Issue (Box 2, Volume 13)
  - The 1978 Girl Scout Engagement Calendar (Box 2, Volume 14)
  - Aramco '74 [yearbook]: Arabian American Oil Company Schools, 1974 (Box 2, Volume 15)
  - "You Discover Saudi Arabia," created by You Discover Inc. [boxed set of items], 1969 (Box 2, Object 16)
    Contents
    Includes one booklet, titled "Getting to Know Saudi Arabia" (New York: Coward-McCann, 1969), miniature flag of Saudi Arabia, one set of worry beads, set of two coins, set of two postage stamps, one printed study guide (11 pages), and set of 24 folded posters, depicting various aspects of the natural history and culture of Saudi Arabia.